<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tactically Creative</title>
    <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Tactically Creative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2015 14:06:07 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tactically Creative&#39;s Ethos</title>
      <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/ethos/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2015 14:06:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/ethos/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Working with Tactically Creative is a different experience for many of our new clients, so we try to make it as easy as possible to get started. We hope that by explaining our Ethos, we can help you understand why we do many of the things the way that we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At TC, we value two ideals above everything else: genuine progress and genuine relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;genuine-progress:0e3963910c2b59d07b806b93acde03ff&#34;&gt;Genuine Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We measure progress by what we produce, not by the time spent working on it. We believe in building something tangible, testing it and refining it. We don&amp;rsquo;t believe in long meetings, trying to scope the unknown or in &amp;ldquo;being busy&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-define-and-strive-for-genuine-progress:0e3963910c2b59d07b806b93acde03ff&#34;&gt;How to define and strive for &amp;ldquo;Genuine Progress&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phrase &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m busy&amp;rdquo; has become the de-facto statement to convey how important you are, and how hard you work. It also seems to be understood that &amp;ldquo;being busy&amp;rdquo; directly equates to positive action and accomplishments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrong! Progress is measured by the results you produce, and the objectives you accomplish; not by taking part in the process that got you there. We aim to work smarter, not harder! We believe that &amp;ldquo;being busy&amp;rdquo; is a sign you&amp;rsquo;re not in control of your project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every business has objectives (or it should!) but no one seems to hold their website to the same standard. A website should have objectives, and we don&amp;rsquo;t believe that endless meetings and scoping documents contribute towards meeting these targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas and strategies that are quickly turned into living, working code and can be immediately implemented, tested and refined are our marker for genuine progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that objective based design and development is the best way to tackle complex projects like websites. Working backwards from your end game and creating a roadmap to follow, you can create a series of milestones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tackling smaller chunks allows us to develop different strategies, experiment, and try out ideas. We can explore multiple ways of reaching your objectives, reviewing the data as we go and definitively being able to say what works and what doesn&amp;rsquo;t; rather than spend a life time speculating in yet another scoping meeting&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;genuine-relationships:0e3963910c2b59d07b806b93acde03ff&#34;&gt;Genuine Relationships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We feel an open, honest and trusting collaboration breeds the best results (and we&amp;rsquo;re all about results). Working relationships shouldn&amp;rsquo;t stop looking like friendships because there&amp;rsquo;s money involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-this-collaboration-actually-means:0e3963910c2b59d07b806b93acde03ff&#34;&gt;What this collaboration actually means&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally treat every client as a friend, which allows us to develop the trusting and honest relationships needed to make the flexible nature of our projects work. There&amp;rsquo;s no heavy-handed contracts, no retainers and no funny business. Not everyone will feel comfortable with such a flexible arrangement, and I completely understand. I work this way because not only are the results exponentially better, we have great fun and make life-long friends on these projects. I feel this is the way business &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be done, even though it rarely is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love seeing our clients succeed, and by allowing us to assist, we get to play a direct role in making that happen. That&amp;rsquo;s the biggest privilege we know of! Whilst our work can provide immediate benefits, we don&amp;rsquo;t subscribe to the notion of &amp;ldquo;quick fixes&amp;rdquo;. Building something great takes time and patience, so we&amp;rsquo;re here for the long haul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-re-different-by-design:0e3963910c2b59d07b806b93acde03ff&#34;&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re different by design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When setting up Tactically Creative, I wanted to improve how websites are built. The pursuit  of that ideal extended to the process and the team involved, and not just the end result. By defining an Ethos for how I believe design, but also business, should be done; I was able to draw my line in the sand. I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to build something that I&amp;rsquo;m incredibly proud of, that remains true to myself and my intentions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Static?</title>
      <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/whystatic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 10:16:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/whystatic/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tl-dr:51226af1ae345d019c3087fd1d561cd1&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, static sites are fast, lightweight, reliable and they scale well. They are more secure, simple to maintain and they allow you to focus all your time and effort on the site&amp;rsquo;s user interface and content. Often, this dedication really shows and places a truly powerful asset at your business&amp;rsquo; disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem is allowing non-technical people a method of updating static sites&amp;hellip;so we fixed that too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Static sites are a much better &lt;strong&gt;asset&lt;/strong&gt; to your business than Wordpress ever could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-serve-your-users-static-web-pages:51226af1ae345d019c3087fd1d561cd1&#34;&gt;Why serve your users static web pages?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, we believe that investing in a static website proves itself worthwhile in every possible way. It&amp;rsquo;s inherent traits mean that we can deliver a website that doesn&amp;rsquo;t distract you from running your business. It allows you to concentrate your efforts on growing and developing, not treading water and maintaining the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to get sucked into the pro/con debate of all of your choices when building a website. There&amp;rsquo;s so many options it&amp;rsquo;s almost paralysing. Fortunately, static sites make a strong case for themselves in a few key areas. Namely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reliability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiency (Return on Investment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoiding excessive detail, here&amp;rsquo;s the reasons why we believe a static solution is best for your growing business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speed:51226af1ae345d019c3087fd1d561cd1&#34;&gt;Speed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be frank, static sites are faster than any dynamic site; purely due to their simplicity. They are lightweight in nature, and can be easily delivered on a cost-effective worldwide platform at incredible speeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speed is really easy to underestimate, but the use of mobile data connections, mobile phones and a shortening of people&amp;rsquo;s attention spans makes your sites loading speed one of the most important metrics to keep an eye on. Many studies have witnessed a very strong and direct correlation between loading speeds and important metrics such as bounce rates, conversion rates and even your revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;insert 5 facts from studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you choose static or not, speed needs to be one of your core considerations from the very beginning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reliability:51226af1ae345d019c3087fd1d561cd1&#34;&gt;Reliability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our favourite reason for going static, as it give us and our clients ultimate peace of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking advantage of static site&amp;rsquo;s inherent simplicity means that we can easily, and cost-effectively provide a very resilient platform for your site. The platform we&amp;rsquo;ve chosen keeps your site running on multiple servers worldwide. Not only does this increase the speed of the site to all users, but it provides total redundancy. If one server goes down; another automatically takes its place. The result? Your site will always be open for business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Redundancy is good, but stopping servers going down in the first place seems like a better idea. A static site is more resilient to traffic surges; meaning that when your site suddenly goes viral, it&amp;rsquo;s prepared to deal with the onslaught of new customers that will come pouring in the front door! How often do you click that trending link on Twitter, only to find an error message stating: &amp;ldquo;This page is unavailable&amp;rdquo;, because their server buckled under the pressure?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;security:51226af1ae345d019c3087fd1d561cd1&#34;&gt;Security&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone&amp;rsquo;s data is digital these days, and dynamic sites that aren&amp;rsquo;t kept secure offer the many villains of the internet a chance to cause mayhem. By inserting malicious code into the pages of your website, without you even knowing, these hackers can bring your site to it&amp;rsquo;s knees. This extra code might do something as simple as add content to your business&amp;rsquo; website that would harm it&amp;rsquo;s reputation (think images and links to some darker corners of the web), or something far more devious such as monitoring and recording your user&amp;rsquo;s activity and data! Quite often, they just delete or modify a few key files that cause the site to go down, and make finding the issue very difficult and time-consuming to resolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;73.2% of the most popular WordPress installations are vulnerable to known exploits which can be detected using free automated tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Static sites aren&amp;rsquo;t totally immune to this sort of attack, but nothing is! However, with no moving parts, and no dynamic processes to interrupt; they often prove to be too much of a challenge for most hackers. Dynamic servers are an easy mark by comparison, and as with outrunning a bear; you don&amp;rsquo;t have to be the fastest, just faster than the other guy&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flexibility:51226af1ae345d019c3087fd1d561cd1&#34;&gt;Flexibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dynamic sites often require you to intricately weave your design and content very closely together, around the platform&amp;rsquo;s own code; in order to provide you with an easy way of updating content on your site. We believe this approach greatly restricts your ability to change and modify the site in years to come, as your business grows. They require you to sacrifice long-term flexibility in order to have access to short-term ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to make that compromise. Not only have we built an incredibly easy and intuitive way to keep your site current (something people wrongly assume can&amp;rsquo;t be done on a static site); it&amp;rsquo;s completely modular! We keep the platform, the design, your content and the editing interface all completely separate to allow your site to grow with you, not tie you down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows you to update and change individual components of the site as you wish, making the website sustainable over a much longer lifetime than one large monolithic system. Do you really want to scrap your entire site every couple of years when it&amp;rsquo;s time for a redesign? Of course you don&amp;rsquo;t! Start building your website in a modular fashion and your outlay becomes a long-lived investment in the future of your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;efficiency:51226af1ae345d019c3087fd1d561cd1&#34;&gt;Efficiency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simplicity is the ultimate sophistication&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a static site that is every bit as powerful as a CMS like Wordpress is not an easy undertaking. Creating such a powerful, yet simple result requires complex and intricate processes; with the considered thought rarely seen in a typical Wordpress setup. It places far more of a burden on us as developers, than any other system would; but we believe the beautiful efficiency it grants is worth it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A static site provides incredible speed without requiring incredibly expensive servers to power it. It provides worldwide reliability because it&amp;rsquo;s naturally lightweight and resilient, whilst keeping running costs low and mitigating the chance of expensive downtime. Security is inherent, meaning less time is spent worrying about attacks, and more time creating and delivering experiences that will delight your customers and grow your business. The modularity of a static site keeps it flexible, and ensures that your investment in your most important asset lasts for as long as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering all of this is a huge task for us, but the resulting site is far more efficient with both your money and you time! How valuable is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-actually-are-static-sites:51226af1ae345d019c3087fd1d561cd1&#34;&gt;What actually are &amp;ldquo;static sites&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand what they are, and how they offer all the benefits that they do; we need to understand a few fundamentals about websites. All web browsers (the thing you&amp;rsquo;re reading this on right now!) understand just three languages, regardless of whether they are a supercomputer, a mobile phone or that crusty of PC you&amp;rsquo;ve got sitting in the loft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can only understand files written as:
* HTML - for the structure and content of the page.
* CSS - for what that page looks like.
* Javascript (JS) - for how the page is animated and interacts with the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the standardised building blocks of the entire internet. Sites can exist with CSS and JS (but not look very pretty), but most utilise all three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of what is going on behind the scenes to create these three types of files, even the most complicated sites such as Facebook, Amazon, Google, etc are reduced to just these three elements before being delivered to your screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-difference-between-static-dynamic:51226af1ae345d019c3087fd1d561cd1&#34;&gt;The Difference Between Static &amp;amp; Dynamic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Static web pages are those consisting of just HTML, CSS and JS. They sit on a server waiting to be called and delivered to your screen in exactly the right format for your browser to understand and display. They are the &amp;lsquo;end result&amp;rsquo;, ready and waiting to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dynamic web pages aren&amp;rsquo;t quite so prepared. When you make a request to a server for a dynamic page, that &amp;lsquo;end result&amp;rsquo; doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually exist yet. It exists only as a skeleton, with a list of parts needed to flesh it out. When the page is requested, the server consults the framework to discover what parts it needs for that particular page. It then sets about finding those parts, and replacing the framework with the proper content, piece by piece, until the entire framework of the page is now filled with the end content. Only now is it ready to send the page your requested to your browser!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the drawback of sites based around dynamic web pages stem from this requirement to rebuild pages upon every request. There are ways to mitigate or reduce the effects, but static will always be faster, safer and more reliable; that&amp;rsquo;s why it&amp;rsquo;s our tool of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>London Fizzle Meetup - June 2015</title>
      <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/post/fizzle-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/post/fizzle-talk/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-brilliant-evening:c9033999b9835a7dfef93e5745ed10aa&#34;&gt;A Brilliant Evening!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I&amp;rsquo;d like to send a big &lt;strong&gt;&amp;lsquo;Thank You!&amp;rsquo;&lt;/strong&gt; to Chris, Rob &amp;amp; Heena who did a wonderful job organising a brilliant event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The online &lt;a href=&#34;http://fizzle.co/?aid=8451&#34;&gt;Fizzle&lt;/a&gt; community is a wonderful resource, full of amazing people doing amazing things; but it really comes to life when you meet these people in person. It was a great honour to be asked to speak in front of them, and share my knowledge of building websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a website is the cornerstone for any online entrepreneur, and it&amp;rsquo;s relevance is becoming greater as time passes. However, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of information out there, which can make the process utterly confusing to the uninitiated. The problem isn&amp;rsquo;t the volume of information though, it&amp;rsquo;s the &amp;lsquo;noise&amp;rsquo; within. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of good advice (signal) and a lot of terrible or irrelevant advice (noise), and separating them can be tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My talk aimed to cut through the noise and deliver a small dose of signal to get everyone started. I decided to write my talk up to serve as a point of reference to everyone there. It has the same content as my talk, plus a bit more. I&amp;rsquo;ve included more advice, along with links to what I feel are the most relevant, and important articles out there for anyone building a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site can be found here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://fizzle-london.netlify.com&#34;&gt;On the Creation of Websites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-line-in-the-sand:c9033999b9835a7dfef93e5745ed10aa&#34;&gt;My line in the sand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may have read in my casestudies, I&amp;rsquo;ve moved away from Content Management Systems like Wordpress for my client work, and have other systems (namely static solutions) that I feel are more suitable. I brought this up during my talk, as &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; talking about technology and platforms was going to tough to avoid. When Wordpress came up, and I spoke about how I don&amp;rsquo;t feel it&amp;rsquo;s the most practical option anymore, I received a healthy dose of skepticism from some of the guys there who use Wordpress themselves. I completely expected that, but the insights that came from the resulting debate were interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually sat down and had this discussion with &lt;em&gt;other developers&lt;/em&gt; before, so it was nice to get into a bit of a debate about the pro&amp;rsquo;s and con&amp;rsquo;s of each option. We know how fervently a developer can defend their platform/language/text editor of choice. We&amp;rsquo;re almost fanatical about our beliefs. Having to justify why I&amp;rsquo;ve abandoned an industry standard like Wordpress and shy away from the heavy-handed contracts that most designers/developers use was a really healthy thing for me to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s clear that I&amp;rsquo;ve drawn my line in the sand, and &lt;strong&gt;I offer what I truly believe to be the best service I can&lt;/strong&gt; for my clients. That&amp;rsquo;s required me to approach problems differently and look beyond the obvious solutions. This goes against the grain, and I&amp;rsquo;m comfortable with that, because I believe in what I&amp;rsquo;m offering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World</title>
      <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/post/helloworld/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 11:57:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/post/helloworld/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Those two immortal words that any developer will know instantly. They symbolise every coffee-fuelled &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Eureka&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; moment and every knowing &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;A-Ha!&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;. They represent learning, understanding and success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fact-1:b0550240c0a1b7c12779ff8220a94c0f&#34;&gt;Fact #1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;Hello World&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; first came about when Brian Kernighan instructed would-be programmers on how to create a simple program, whose only purpose is to output those two little words. The phrase originates from a passage in his book; &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;A Tutorial to the Language B&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;. That was in 1972, and since then, &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Hello World&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; has come represent many programmers and developers first steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has become the de-facto result that novices create when learning basic computer science principles, or even when experienced professionals are learning a new language. It is the proof of concept, and a gateway to ever-increasing knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember my first &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;HW&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; was written in Visual Basic, which my uncle taught me as a child. Once I had that cracked, it was a short step to building a calculator, mimicking Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s own; and then onto larger, complex database driven systems. That &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Hello World&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; became the starting point for the rest of my professional life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fact-2:b0550240c0a1b7c12779ff8220a94c0f&#34;&gt;Fact #2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;tactically-creative-is-here:b0550240c0a1b7c12779ff8220a94c0f&#34;&gt;Tactically Creative is here!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst Tactically Creative has only officially been around for a few months, this moment has been a long time coming! About two years ago, I set out with a mission of making websites for small businesses easier to use, less of a productivity blackhole and far more cost effective. I wanted people to *gasp* enjoy building their website again, rather than dreading the mine-field of publishing new content and making changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Tactically Creative exists to make building and maintaining your business website a breeze, and also fun again! We focus specifically on developing static sites and web apps that provide huge advantages over the go-to solution of Wordpress or similar CMS. We believe that static sites are increasingly the best solution for many businesses, and whilst that idea swims against the current; we&amp;rsquo;re here to show you that the status-quo isn&amp;rsquo;t all it&amp;rsquo;s cracked up to be!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s to &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Hello World&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Persian Pursuits</title>
      <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/casestudy/persianpursuits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 15:07:16 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/casestudy/persianpursuits/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Travel is rightly considered to be one of the most educational and
liberating experiences a person can pursue. It’s hard to compete with
exploring a new, unfamiliar place and the excitement that brings;
particularly when that travel takes you away from the hotel complexes
and far off the beaten track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charity challenges and the publicity surrounding them such as the Sport
Relief climb of Kilimanjaro a few years ago and more recently Alex
Jones’ ascent Moonlight Buttress in Yosemite National Park, have
prompted companies offering treks to far flung places to up their game.
There is now huge competition in the marketplace, and everyone has been
forced to come up with new, exotic and sometimes weirdly themed treks
and adventures for the traveller with wanton wanderlust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very familiar with these adventures, having taken
part in a few for charity, and possessing the same insatiable urge to
travel. When I was approached by Shirin Shabestari to help build the
website for her new idea, Persian Pursuits; I was instantly intrigued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an Iranian woman now living in the UK, she wanted to promote Iran and
it’s wonderful mountains as a destination for the adventurous traveller.
Rather than compete with the much larger trekking companies and their
machine gun approach to adventure, she wanted to offer a more restrained
and personal experience of her country. She wanted people to experience
and understand Iran the way she did, and balance the often negative
media coverage from Western countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She wanted her fledgling business to offer small, personal trips to Iran
for people to experience it’s mountains, Damavand in particular; and
show off the wonderful culture to be found in the capital, Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/images/qtctc_asset_persianpursuits.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Shirin of Persian Pursuits in Iran&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-blank-canvas:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;A Blank Canvas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having worked for Action Challenge, a company offering charity treks and
challenges; I was extremely familiar with the concept, and what the
counter movement that Shirin was proposing meant. However, my work
building websites at Action Challenge was going to be far removed from
the blank slate that Persian Pursuits offered. I was used to building
sites with very tight restrictions, and with CMSs that were already very mature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, the prospect of creating something new and different got me
really excited about the project’s potential. It was a chance to promote
a beautiful country that had yet to be spoilt by large amounts of
tourism, and offer the chance to experience it in a genuine and
sustainable way. This was completely in-keeping with my views on travel,
that I couldn’t wait to get started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew that successfully creating a site that did Persian Pursuits
justice would require me to focus on the specific needs of the business,
rather than what has already been done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;different-needs:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;Different needs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site would require all the standard trappings of a travel business.
There would need to be a way to easily add information about upcoming
trips, and easily organise them. The trip listings would need to be
standardised in a template to ensure that there was consistency between
listings, and to assist the clarity of communication. This was nothing
out of the ordinary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, unlike many well known trekking destinations, Iran is quite
unfamiliar to most people. They know very little about it generally, and
even less about what’s required to travel there. Shirin also informed me
that the process of obtaining a visa to travel is complex, and subject
to illogical and unexplained change at short notice. This can be
off-putting to many potential visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear that there was room to establish a good knowledge base of
information about traveling to Iran to support Persian Pursuits’ treks,
and provide reassurance to those unsure about making it their
destination of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also decided quite early on that a blog documenting past trips would
be a very useful tool. It would allow the knowledge base to remain 100%
factual and quite dry, with more anecdotal advice being published in the
blog. It would also act as key selling point when potential customers
were browsing the site if there were detailed write-ups of past trips to
compliment the information about upcoming ones. Most importantly, it
would allow Shirin to develop Persian Pursuits as an authority on the
subject of traveling to Iran; something the young business would benefit
from hugely should the established travel companies make a move into
Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;old-v-new:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;Old v New&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When working at Action Challenge, these sorts of sites had always been
supported by a heavily modified Wordpress installation with lots of
plugins, or a completely bespoke CMS. I wanted to explore whether I
could build something to offer the same functionality with my new CMS
of choice, Statamic. For those who don’t know Statamic, it&amp;rsquo;s a flat-file
CMS; meaning that it doesn’t require a database. This makes it a much
simpler system to work with, both in the development stages, but also
further down the line when changes, or ammendments to content is
required. However, it doesn’t allow for the complex arranging and
filtering of information that a database does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew Statamic was more than capable of the project, but I had yet to
build anything of this nature with it. Previously, I had reserved it
for smaller publishing or blogging websites, but had been impressed by
it’s capabilities. It was time to see what Statamic could do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;focus-on-templates-build-from-there:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;Focus on templates…build from there&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear that this website would need to sustain the company through
it’s early years, and once it was online; would receive very little
attention. Shirin was a busy woman, and just running the trips was a
full-time job in itself. Promoting the business as well would leave her
extremely pushed for time. I needed to ensure that the site wouldn’t
slow her down, and make adding and editing content a breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I aimed to make it as modular as possible so that it scaled easily,
both horizontally and vertically; and ensure that once it was released
it was ‘right’. Whilst I usually advocate a process of slow, constant
refinement; it was clear that this wasn’t the correct approach for
Persian Pursuits. Once it was live, that was it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;stumbling-block-future-proof:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;Stumbling block - future proof&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My desire to make it future proof meant that I focussed heavily on
building templates that were relevant to the future of the company, as
well as their current needs. Just because Persian Pursuits current trips
ran once a year, I wanted to ensure that multiple dates could be added.
I examined not only the content that Shirin might need to publish now,
but the content she would need to publish in the years to come. This was
quite a difficult process, as not only was I speculating the future
needs of the business, I was doing so with almost zero legacy
information to base my decisions on. With hindsight, this was a
mistake, as both Shirin and I became sidetracked by the
‘possible’, rather than the ‘actual’ needs of the business; and
generating strong, engaging content and experiences got sidelined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something that became a problem at Action Challenge too. It
might be the nature of the travel industry, where it’s requirements of a
website are very focussed on the future. Whether it’s an inherent trait
or not, we recognised that we had become victim of the dreaded
“paralysis by over-analysis”. This had entirely derailed projects at
Action Challenge, where no one had the experience to stop them, analyse
the situation and put a plan of action in place to resolve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I hadn’t written a great deal of code, and all of the
concepts were static mockups made in Photoshop and Sketch. I decided
that the solution to this situation was revert to the iterative process
I usually use, and in a moment of madness had abandoned for this
project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;design-in-code:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;Design in code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I immediately transcribed our latest mockup into code, and worked from
there. This initial prototype was certainly far from perfect and barely
functional in places. Many problems with the user-interface became
apparent as soon as we started working with dynamic prototypes, and we
realised that we had made some of the templates too constrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst areas of the site such as the trip listings benefitted from the
highly structured templates we had made; others such as the knowledge
base didn’t. As I was uncertain about the nature of the content, I
had struggled to build these templates without resorting to guesswork.
The result was a set of templates for the knowledge base that were
highly opinionated, yet didn’t match the actual content Shirin wanted
published for launch. The answer was to scrap the highly opinionated
templates for this area of the site, and move forward with a far more
open and generic method of inputing content that would allow greater
flexibility. Perhaps, once the knowledge base was more established, less
generic templates would be of benefit, but for the time being; they
proved to be ideal solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project&amp;rsquo;s codebase became highly modular, and built outwards from the core
functionality of the site. New features either extended or modified
pre-existing styles. This was a process I had used when developing
previous sites when there was very little data to support decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instantly, the site became more cohesive with a better sense of
identity. This is the advantage of designing in the browser with code.
Everything becomes bound together, so you lose disparate elements that
fight with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when I coded features that were later rejected, the code that was
written for these features usually became of use elsewhere. Unlike
design that is highly specific, code (when written well) can be
extremely modular and recycled for use outside it’s original intent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intervention and the return to my preferred process took a
floundering project that was falling behind schedule, and gave it
the direction to get it back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;results:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the purpose of the site was always to act as a resource of
information for Persian Pursuits’ trips to Iran, and get people booked
on to trips; it actually accomplished much more as the public face of
the company. Shirin had previously had great success using just Facebook
to represent her company, but it always lacked a sense of authority, and
lots of interest in trips would fizzle out. By creating a focal point
for her thriving Facebook page to direct leads to, she gave Persian
Pursuits far more credibility and a louder voice with which to promote
travel to Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also been very successful as a tool to promote Shirin and the work
that she does. The site, along with her monumental persistence, gave her
a credibility that allowed her to be chosen as a speaker for the Royal
Geographical Society, and receive sponsorship and support from a number
of outdoor equipment manufacturers. Even more impressively, she has a
video in the pipeline in conjunction with Hot Aches productions taking
place on her upcoming ‘Damavand Winter’ trip in April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-learnt:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;What I Learnt&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;real-code-is-what-counts:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;Real code is what counts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designing mockups is always great fun. You have a suite of tools readily
at your disposal that help you create designs quickly and easily, and
don’t hinder the flow of your ideas. Code slows down this process, and
makes it less natural; which is why it’s tempting to do as much design
as possible before hitting the code editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue is that sometime problems with the design don’t surface until
you get code into the browser. You can end up redesigning a lot of
features that have previously been signed off as ‘done’. Not only is it
demoralising, it’s a waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless I find a clear reason against it, I will continue getting my
designs into code as quickly as possible. Ideally I would like to get to a
stage where not only the final few elements are added whilst coding, but
the vast majority of the site makes it’s debut in code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;start-small:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;Start small&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project grew quickly. It actually overtook us, and started to run
away a little. It was very easy, and tempting, to focus on what the site
‘could’ do; rather than what it ‘should’. It’s a subtle change in
thinking, but one that caused the project to derail. Only by
coming back to what mattered right in the here and now did I wrest it
under control again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;be-bold-rectify-mistakes-later:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;Be bold, rectify mistakes later&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Paralysis by over-analysis” is real. I thought when I was at
Action Challenge that it occurred due to the strung out nature of an
inexperienced in-house team trying to collaborate with a design agency
based hundreds of miles away. As it turns out, it can strike in much
smaller teams, and is just as dangerous to a project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had previously worked in ways that avoided this paralysis by making
decisions, putting them in code and testing them out as fast as
possible. I aimed to fail as fast as possible to rule out what didn’t
work, and to prove what did. By avoiding this iteration and trying to
get it ‘right’ first time whilst in the design stage, the projects just stopped
making progress; instead going around and around in circles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ps-these-write-ups-matter:70204a93cd31b77ad138ccbf296b4331&#34;&gt;PS: These write-ups matter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing up my case studies can sometime take a few hours by the time
it’s been reviewed, edited and uploaded. It would be far easier to just
add a few photos of my work to a portfolio with a quick paragraph
explaining what I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I’ve found that these longer, more insightful case studies
help me refine and develop my process. They highlight what parts were
successful and should be incorporated into my next project, and which
parts caused any issues I had encountered. I got this project back on
track when I revisited Jake Morrell’s project and had to amend my
writeup. What I found in that writeup informed my choices in this
project, and allowed me to identify the steps that I needed to take to get
it back on course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing this particular case study has highlighted more failures than
successes in my process, but it had also allowed me to learn from them.
Sometimes to only way to improve is to pick yourself back up, and work
out why you fell over in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jake Morrell</title>
      <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/casestudy/jakemorrell/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 15:07:03 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/casestudy/jakemorrell/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A band’s need of a website is not uncommon, but finding the right
website can prove tricky for the uninitiated. A band’s site functions
very much as a small business’ site does, yet without the clear &amp;amp; direct
financial objective; which can make it very difficult to build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site also has to become the band’s online ‘home’ that grows with
them. Needing something so personal makes finding an off-the-shelf
solution tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/images/qtctc_asset_jakeband.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Jake Morrell&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;country-roots:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Country roots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Jake Morrell approached me, he was a musician who had recently
decided that his band should start taking their music seriously, and
start building up a reputation and solid fanbase. Up until that point,
he had been an enthusiastic and talented musician, but had yet to treat
his music as a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the decision was made to make a go of it, Jake recognised that his
current website was not up to the task. If he wanted the band to grow in
popularity, it was clear that their website needed attention if it was
to capture everything that was brilliant about their music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;templates-without-soul:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Templates without soul&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve already said, finding an off-the-shelf solution for a website
as personal as a band’s can be really tough; even more-so when that
band’s identity &amp;amp; sound is as unique and different as Jake’s. He had
been finding that none of the templates and themes he had found really
felt ‘right’ for his band, and the designer in him kept thinking there
must be a better alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He wanted to avoid becoming ‘just another band’, and blending in with
the herd. Jake’s music instantly solves that issue in the flesh, but how
could he stand out online? After looking through his options, he was
confidant that a theme or template, no matter how well designed and
built could never quite capture the band’s identity and their
aspirations for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jake wanted a site that would act as a hub for all his online
communication with his fanbase. Social media was working well in
generating interest, but without a focal point it was lacking impact.
Consolidating his band’s identity into a central site would allow him to
manage and cultivate the band’s image as it grew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also had a problem with his current site that needed solving; he
couldn’t update it! If the site was to grow and become the band’s focal
point, it would need to be simple to update and keep current. The
existing site also didn’t offer any responsive design elements for
mobile viewers. Jake had no analytics to confirm that many of his views
came from portable devices, but was fairly sure that a significant
percentage would have benefited from it. That instantly told me that I
needed to incorporate responsive design into the build, but also some
analytics tools to provide data for later optimisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-new-perspective:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;A new perspective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with a band was a new experience for me. Whilst I&amp;rsquo;m very
comfortable working with small businesses and their objectives; I was
left scratching my head when it came to the music industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where a strong process and working relationship between clients
and their designers comes into play. I could have gone away and done
mounds of research on the music industry and discovered what makes a
successful website in this industry. That would have given me a very
broad overview of the issues facing Jake, but would have left me
with exactly that: a broad view. I needed specific, actionable insights
into Jake’s industry, and what issues it was that he saw and needed
solving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By working closely with Jake throughout, I was able to use him as the
project’s compass. He would indicate a direction or potential problem;
and I would dig through the available data and come up with a suitable,
relevant solution. I’ll happily hold me hands up and say that I
missed the mark on occasions, which only proves why I advocate a close
and ongoing relationship with clients. Any wrong turns
were quickly identified in our regular meetings and conversations, and
we got back on track with little time or resources lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-personal-touch:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;The personal touch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designing an experience for something as personal as a band’s site was
always going to be a challenge. In business, often data and good
practises based on the financial objectives for the site can inform much
of the design. The design decisions for a band, or any personal site,
can be much more arbitrary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I was concerned whether I was the right choice for Jake,
as there are other design companies who concentrate on this sector
exclusively. However, he already had a very clear vision of what he
wanted from the site. What he needed from me was the knowledge and
experience needed to make the strong visual direction he had decided
upon a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an experienced designer (career pre-music) Jake took on the design
himself. The results had exactly the right tone and atmosphere that
suited the band down to the ground. It needed to be simple, honest and
friendly; all sentiments that were captured perfectly because they came
direct from the original source of the band’s identity: Jake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;over-to-me-act-i:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Over to Me - Act I&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This left me focussing heavily on the technical side of the site. When
Jake initially approached me he was asking for a site based on the
almost ubiquitous platform, Wordpress. As I had extensive experience
creating and managing Wordpress sites, I started without a second thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jake’s two key prerequisites were responsive design, and an easy way of
updating the site regularly. Whilst Wordpress was (and always has) been
geared around ‘Posts’, I knew that ‘Custom Post Types’ and various
other plugins would provide the functionality we required for managing
content such as a listing of Jake’s upcoming gigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsive design was something that I had worked with before, but
never from the ‘ground up’ on a new build. For this reason I used a popular and well
documented framework: Foundation. This gave me a good solid system to
work from, and an array of elements that would cover the initial site
build, and any future feature requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt that using two widely available, well established pillars of the
web development world would give Jake a future proof website that could
be easily worked on by almost any developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-wrong-turn:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;A wrong turn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foundation provided a very strong framework to begin building on, however
it was not without it’s problems. Most popular frameworks such as
Bootstrap and Foundation are quite opinionated as standard, and I found
myself overriding much of Foundation’s default styling. This was, I
felt, was a price worth paying to keep the site’s codebase future proof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, once I had completed the site and began testing it, I became
increasingly upset with what I had made. Whilst Jake was very happy
with the site, I felt that the code supporting it was heavy,
overworked, and thanks to the number of overrides required; far less
future-proof than I had hoped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To top it off, I felt that Wordpress, as with Foundation, was too
prescriptive for this project. It forced upon us the notion of ‘Posts’,
when really we wanted nothing of the sort! The editing interface was, as
with all Wordpress sites, very ‘messy’. Wordpress as standard displays
far too many options and menu items for someone who wants to update
their gigs and write the odd blog post. This can of course be hidden
away, but why should we have to distort the system like this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew that Jake was self-hosting the site, and I likely wouldn’t have any
input on the site once it was launched. This begged the question of how
to manage the Wordpress updates. Did I really want to burden Jake
with updating the install and it’s associated plugins himself, or having
to get me to do it periodically; just to keep the site secure? All of
this seemed unnecessary for what should be a simple site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back to the drawing board…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-me-act-ii:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Back to Me - Act II&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I wanted to resolve was the restrictions that Wordpress
was imposing on the site. It was bloated, complicated and needlessly
complex for this project; so I set out to find the antithesis of this.
I was sure that the answer would be found in ditching the database,
and relying on ‘static’ web pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, I had been playing around with the static site generator,
Jekyll. For those unfamiliar, Jekyll takes templates written in Liquid,
combines that with content files written in Markdown, and builds the
site into flat, static HTML documents. This results in an incredibly
fast, stable site that can be hosted almost anywhere. Jekyll was always
considered a blogging tool for ‘hackers’, but it’s press as the basis of
Obama’s online fundraising campaign has caused a resurgence in the
popularity of static sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had enough experience building small, quick sites with it to know
that it would work well in this situation; the only issue was how to add
content in a non technical manner. At that time, there was no easy way
to manage content in non-technical manner, everything was done through
Markdown files. I needed something with a suitable interface for Jake
to easily keep the site current, and manage logic surrounding gig listings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution came in the form of a half-way house between Wordpress and
Jekyll: a flat-file CMS called Statamic. Whilst akin to Wordpress in
functionality, it had a structure far closer to a pre-build Jekyll site;
using templates, YAML config files and Markdown content files to
dynamically render the page. Fortunately, Statamic has brilliant
HTML-rendered caching, effectively allowing the site to serve static files to
users, but with a dynamic twist when required. This provided the all
important GUI for Jake to work with, and a lightweight system that could
output static files in most instances, reducing load times and improving
the user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My concern over Foundation caused me to take a deeper look at the way I
build my websites. I no longer considered an all-encompassing
framework to be a universal ally. Foundation, like Bootstrap, works well
for quick prototyping but, as I found; poorly in production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution came from creating a bespoke, SASS-based framework loosely
based Harry Robert’s InuitCSS. I used Object-Orientated-CSS (OOCSS)
methodology to build functionality ‘outwards’ from the core of what the
site needed to do right now; rather than ‘inwards’ from a rather
speculative position of what the site &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; need to do in the future.
The result was a lightweight, fast, highly extensible and future proof
framework that could support the site for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-semi-static-renaissance:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;A Semi-Static Renaissance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results speak for themselves. Not only does Jake prefer the vastly
simplified user-interface of Statamic, but the performance meets my
expectations. We’ve managed to achieve some solid loading times, and
Statamic has proved incredibly stable, with straightforward development.
I hope to spend more time with Statamic in the upcoming months to make
it even faster for my clients and their users, as I feel it has great
promise as my “go to” solution for small websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of a database means that the site is far less vulnerable to
security risks, and whilst theoretically still at risk due to the
dynamic nature of the site; it is far, far less likely to be
compromised. In the event it is, getting the site back online is as
simple as replacing some files in a directory, which is the work of 10
minutes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OOCSS framework has allowed for simple ongoing development of the
site. Adding new features is simple, as they either extend or modify
existing ones, or bolt-on with no complications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-learned:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;What I Learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;wordpress-is-not-the-solution:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Wordpress is not the solution&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After exploring various CMS options, I have concluded that Wordpress
should no longer be my standard solution, as in most cases, it’s
probably not the best tool for the job. In fact, the more time I spend
with other systems such as Statamic, and static-site-generators (SSGs);
the more I believe that Wordpress will very rarely be the best tool for
my projects now, if ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;an-intelligent-css-architecture-is-worth-it-s-weight-in-gold:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;An intelligent CSS architecture is worth it’s weight in gold.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s probably not the best way to articulate what I&amp;rsquo;m trying to say,
as such an architecture probably weighs next to nothing! However, it
can’t be denied that a considered approach to writing (S)CSS pays
dividends the longer you expect a website to last. Having a well written
one is not only beneficial for performance and ease of development
initially, but can prove to be cost-saving in the long term, when
compared to refactoring the CSS over the lifetime of a website to
accommodate new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;communication-is-key:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Communication is key&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learnt so much on this project, both generally, but also from Jake.
I learnt how to deal with the objectives of a website when there’s no
direct financial correlation to site performance and it’s traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most important thing I learnt was that my process of
constant communication and involvement with the client directly, can’t
be undervalued. Compared to, perhaps more ‘traditional’, methods of
running a project where the client is kept at arms-length and
periodically presented to; the new approach saved both Jake and I time,
and meant we were both much happier with the final outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-03-march-2015:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Update: 03 March 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I thought I’d attach a quick update to this case study. I’ve
continued work on Jake’s site over the past few months, something
neither of us thought would happen. This ongoing work is partly due to
the affinity that I feel towards the project and the band, but also the
results that I’ve produced.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working further on optimising the site and the server setup for
Statamic, I’ve been able to achieve some incredible page load times
(~200ms from a cold cache!). This sort of speed increase has
dramatically improved the UX of the site, and it’s suitability for use
on mobile devices; even those with slow connections!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My work with Statamic on subsequent projects has also confirmed that
Wordpress is no longer a relevant tool for my work. I’ve completely
fallen for Statamic and other static systems. I’ve since updated all of
my previous client work to be based on Statamic at zero cost. Replacing
the legacy Wordpress sites from my portfolio was a large time
investment for me, but completely worth it. All my clients are
reporting that they love the new CMS, and it means that I can manage
fewer systems. Everyone wins!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Calum Mallory</title>
      <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/casestudy/calummallory/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 15:06:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/casestudy/calummallory/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Calum Mallory is an individual with some extraordinary interests, and
the skills to go with them. He describes himself as a “climber, alpinist
&amp;amp; mountaineer”, and he certainly lives up to all three titles! Since
2013, he has been working towards tackling his biggest challenge: Mount
Everest. I was thrilled when he asked me to help out with this
journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/images/qtctc_asset_calum.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Calum Mallory - Climber&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-i-met-calum:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;When I met Calum…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t lie, I was a touch disappointed when it turned out he wanted
me to make a website, and not go on the climb with him! C&amp;rsquo;est la vie!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first met Calum when learning how to ice-climb. Calum was my instructor, and over a number of weeks
taught me how to become an ice-climbing instructor myself at Ellis
Brigham’s indoor ice wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Calum mentioned he was planning on climbing Mt. Everest, and needed
some help getting together a website and promotional materials to help
raise funds for the trip, I immediately offered to help. Not only did
I have experience building websites for charity focussed expeditions
with Action Challenge, but couldn’t resist taking on such a different
project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-started:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Getting started…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the site had the clear purpose of promoting Calum as a climber,
and raising funds for his expedition, it was also a very personal site.
Fresh from my recent work with Jake Morrell and his band, personal
sites were definitely at the front of my mind, and I quickly started building a brand for Calum and his exploits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branding is something that I rarely do. By the time most companies
start working with me, their brand is already well established and very
little can change. As with my work with Jake Morrell, I was stepping
out of my comfort zone yet again, and testing my skills in a different
area of design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After conducting some initial research into similar sites and campaigns,
an issue that both Calum and I agreed on, and were concerned
with; was the &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; of the brand. We wanted to avoid getting caught up
with the “extreme sport” angle of what Calum does. Given the nature of
his work, and his age; it would have been all too easy to punch out some
relatively generic brand and site that catered to the extreme sport
market, but did nothing to differentiate Calum from his peers. Being
quite inexperienced with brand design, I was concerned that there was
a danger that we could slide towards comfortable stereotypes, even
whilst conscious of this potential pitfall. Throughout the process, I
pledged to remain vigilant for cliches and stereotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst Calum is young, his personality and his attitude towards climbing
are far more mature. He’s incredibly understated and lets his climbing
do all the talking. The only thing that perforates this calm, considered
personality is his enthusiasm for climbing. It’s clear when you meet him
that climbing &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; his life. I immediately associated him with an era
of climbing when it wasn’t about all the shiny, high-tech kit and the
sponsorship deals; but was much purer, and just about the climbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those familiar with outdoor brands, I felt he was more
&lt;strong&gt;Patagonia&lt;/strong&gt;, than &lt;strong&gt;Arcteryx&lt;/strong&gt;. With that in mind, I began basing his
image around the old ‘Chouinard’ brand that eventually evolved into
Patagonia. I took inspiration from the colours that are now considered
‘vintage’ &amp;amp; ‘retro’, and set out to keep the design restrained &amp;amp;
purposeful, much like the industrial design of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-logo:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;The logo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A logo is a logical place to start when designing a brand, and it’s
always a thought-provoking process. The fundamentals are the same as
copy-writing. You condense everything about the company or person, into
as few visual elements as possible, whilst still communicating as much
as possible. This distillation process results in simplicity, which has
a far greater chance of being understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to engage a passer-by, a logo must not only be aesthetically
simple, but also have hidden or implied meaning and content. This often
presents itself as wit or humour, and rewards the passer-by for their
attention, and prompts them to engage further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst there are similarities between brand and website design, they are
also wildly different! It’s fair to say that logos are not my cup of
coffee…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, rather than consult a logo designer, Calum opted for me to have
a crack at it first; as he loved the enthusiasm that I had for the
project. I decided to tackle it exactly as I do with the rest of my
design: slowly and iteratively. Instead of hoping for some divine flash
of inspiration (as any creative will tell you, they are rare and not to
be relied upon) I chose to start with a logo that Calum liked during
our research, and iterate from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed was a series of logos that started out rather ugly but had
a solid idea behind them; and were then slowly refined. We felt our
resulting logo communicated enough about his work, without straying
towards the extreme sports angle we feared might be a result. By
starting with a very simple idea, and slowly (and carefully) refining
it, only adding what was necessary; we ended up with something that we
feel represents Calum personality perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;content:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calum was really enthusiastic about the website once he saw the brand
coming together. He began flooding my inbox with photos we could use and
content that could make up the website. It was a refreshing change, as
often website projects suffer from not enough, or irrelevant content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, content is the hardest part of the site to crack. It’s certainly
the most crucial, and without it; all attempts at design fall a little
flat. With Calum supplying so much raw material to work with, I could
be quite ruthless with the edit. I wanted to concentrate
Calum’s message into as fewer words as possible, but not so few that
the communication was compromised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, Calum found this approach to editing a little
brutal, and felt I was cutting too much. However, as the content
slowly started coalescing into pages &amp;amp; paragraphs, he saw that
concentrating what he was saying into as few words as possible worked.
What was left had impact, and engaged the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the logo development, I had also created a number of other
vectors. We agreed that it would be a shame for these not to make
the cut, so they became part of the page layout. They added visual
elements other than photos, which was a point of difference to Calum’s
competition. Their sites were incredibly image heavy, and felt a little
bogged down by them both technically and editorially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;video:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One element however would dwarf the rest of the content. Calum had been
working with his climbing partner, Molly Hughes, and Mark Leary, a video
director; to create a short video to summarise the team, their
personality and the challenge that they faced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear as soon as the video was mentioned that it would play a
large role in the site’s experience. I knew that the two would have to
compliment each other and work together. If we ended up with a video
that fought with the website around it, the experience could be
confusing and all the good work we had done with Calum in developing his
brand would be compromised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was decided that we should have a chat with Mark, and find out his
plans for the video, and his thoughts on the brand that we had
developed. Fortunately, we found ourselves on the same page. When Mark
explained his plan for the video, I couldn’t help but nod my head the
entire way through!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bringing-it-together:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Bringing it together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video was finished just before the launch of the site, and I got
my first look at it only a day before the site was due to go live.
After my earlier chat with Mark, I knew there was nothing to worry about,
and that the website and the video would work well together; but I had
no idea just how well the two would gel!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-learned:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;What I learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;have-fun:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Have fun!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project was a chance to have some fun. Calum was incredibly relaxed
about the project, and was enjoying his first taste of building a
website. The hardest part of the process was getting feedback from
Calum, as it was hard to get him to be critical of our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was more apparent was the joy I found in tackling something as
different as a portfolio website for an ice-climbing adventurer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;don-t-let-business-get-in-the-way:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Don’t let business get in the way!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that the site definitely felt more like a personal project than
client work at times. This caused me to stray from the brief on
occasions, and drop many of the fundraising features that were initially
present in the brief. After discussing these omissions with Calum, it
was concluded that we should stick with the site we had built. He liked
that it was his personal space to document his growth as a climber and
the exciting trips he went on; and not a transcription of the various
fundraising pages he was already using. It was different, and by having
that ‘portfolio’ to refer to, it made his fundraising pages stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;let-things-develop-naturally:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Let things develop naturally.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throwing myself into brand design was a challenge. It was not
entirely new territory for me, but certainly ground that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t as familiar with. However, by taking the same iterative process
that I use for web development, I think we cracked it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always had an end in mind, but I let the route to that aesthetic
goal develop slowly. This careful approach posed many more questions
than I had anticipated, and brought to light some interesting ideas
that I had not considered previously. Take your time, and the result
will be evidence of that care and attention.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terms &amp; Conditions</title>
      <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 13:23:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/terms/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;every-project-we-undertake-is-subject-to-our-t-cs-we-know-it-s-a-bore-but-please-read-them-before-we-work-together:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;Every project we undertake is subject to our T&amp;amp;Cs. We know it&amp;rsquo;s a bore, but please read them before we work together.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst we would really rather go about our business without any terms &amp;amp; conditions, we regrettably have to put some in place. If you feel any of the following prevent you from working with us, get in touch and we’ll talk about it. Any amendments to these T&amp;amp;Cs must be made in advance and agreed upon in writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following terms &amp;amp; conditions apply to all services provided by Tactically Creative, and by ordering any of our services; you are agreeing to adhere to the following T&amp;amp;C’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-contract-commencement:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;1 - Contract Commencement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is likely that some of our work together will occur before we agree on a suitable contract for our engagement. If any of this work is to be charged for, we will notify you before proceeding; and our temporary engagement shall be subject to all the terms and conditions listed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we have agreed the nature of our project together, a suitable contract shall be put in place detailing the parties subject to the contract, the work to be carried out, an estimated price, predicted completion dates and a payment schedule. It should be understood that any requests for changes or additions outside the original agreement shall be subject to a change order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any price estimates are valid for thirty days only, and all predicted completion dates shall be subject to change, based on when the project commenced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst we aim to have both parties sign this contract to confirm their agreement to it, we recognise this is not always possible. In this instance, a clear written confirmation (via email or otherwise) of agreement to the contract and its adjoining terms &amp;amp; conditions, along with payment of the initial deposit; shall constitute commencement of the contract and a contractual agreement between the client and Tactically Creative shall exist based on the quotation with its specifications and these terms and conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactically Creative cannot always guarantee to start work immediately on a project but will arrange a date with the client as to when work can commence. An anticipated finishing date will be agreed and Tactically Creative will endeavour to adhere to it, but cannot guarantee to do so in the light of circumstances outside of our control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where in the instance that a time scale has been agreed, Tactically Creative will not be responsible for any consequential losses to the client if the deadline is not met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-our-process:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;2 - Our Process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will work with you closely in a collaborative process from the very start of the project. Much of our work requires us to have an intimate knowledge of your products or services, and the goals you want to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we work in a collaborative, ‘Agile’ manner, we require that you are available to work directly with us on a number of occasions. Our style of work means that we work together ‘with you’, rather than ‘for you’; which ultimately will lead to greater benefits for your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst this style of project can produce brilliant results, it can be very hard to distinguish developments of an idea that is within scope, from a change or new feature that exists outside our agreement. When this occurs, we will make you aware of the feature or change that we feel falls outside our agreement before starting work on it; and offer to include it as part of a change order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a particular element, feature or functionality within our agreement requires lots of ongoing development and refinement beyond what could be considered reasonable, we will propose a process where we discuss and re-evaluate the item that is causing delays. This is to either clarify our understanding of the item’s purpose, or to ascertain whether it is actually necessary at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, this process is not one where you are given a set number of revisions, limited opportunities to provide feedback and instruct us what to do. A fluid process such as ours, with so many opportunities for discussion, collaboration and ongoing amendments, which can become grey areas; is unfortunately open to abuse if either party is unreasonable. We ask that when working with us, you are fair, reasonable and honest with your requests; and we shall do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the project meets the specification within the contract, it is deemed ‘complete’; and any further amendments to the product (design, functionality or otherwise) will be at the discretion of Tactically Creative if a maintenance agreement is not present. It is at this point that any remaining balance for the project is due.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a project is complete and total payment has been made, we will make the production files available to you, or alternatively upload them to your public server. Until that time, and whilst we are working on them, your website and its updates will be available for review on our development server only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-change-orders:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;3 - Change Orders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, if you decide on additional work outside of our existing agreement; we will draw up a change order. This will definitively list the changes or additions to our pre-existing arrangement, the associated cost involved and adjusted deadlines. Both parties must agree to this change order, either by signing, or confirming their agreement in writing as detailed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that maintenance and service agreements are not subject to change orders, and remain binding for the predetermined period set out in the specific contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-services:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;4 - Services&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactically Creative also offer a number of ongoing services in addition to the ‘Projects’ we undertake for the client. These rolling services are ‘Website Maintenance’, ‘Website Hosting’ &amp;amp; ‘A/B Testing’. Each of these services are subject to their own, separate contracts; and unless an agreement is made specifically for any of these services, they are not included within a Project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactically Creative require that the client commits to an initial three month period of provision for each service. Once this initial three month period has passed, the arrangement continues on a monthly, rolling basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Payment for the initial three month period must be made in advance, before the service in question shall be provided. Payments thereafter, are due one month in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For example, payment for services running 1 April - 30 April shall be due on 1 March.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Failure to make this payment within our standard 30 day period, shall result in a suspension of the client’s service. Tactically Creative reserve the right at our sole and absolute discretion to withdraw any services that we would otherwise be obliged to provide; when payment has not been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the client wishes to cancel a service, they will be required to give at least one months notice in writing (email is acceptable) to Tactically Creative. They will however be entitled to continue using the provided service until the end of the period that has been paid for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Using the above example, if the payment was due on 1 March for services running 1 April - 30 April, the client must inform Tactically Creative that they wish to cancel before 31 March. They will however be entitled to the use of the service until 30 April&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the client wises to cancel a service within the initial three month period, it is understood that the client is not entitled to a refund, partial or otherwise; but are entitled to continue using the service until the end of the three month window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where Tactically Creative cancels a service contract other than for a reason set out in Cancellation and Termination below, a refund equivalent to the unused portion of the current payment period will be the maximum liability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-1-website-maintenance:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;4.1 - Website Maintenance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where Tactically Creative undertakes to maintain or update a client’s website; a suitable system of communication shall be established to allow for the ongoing development of the client’s site. The specific details of the work that Tactically Creative will carry out as part of this agreement will be listed in the specific contract pertaining to ongoing maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In instances where the client does not come to a web site management agreement it is the sole responsibility of the client to manage the site. Tactically Creative will no longer be responsible for the site upon completion unless an alternative agreement has been reached. In the absence of a maintenance agreement, Tactically Creative will fix all errors notified to us in writing within thirty days of the site being put live on the Internet. If errors are reported after more than thirty days, the time and costs involved in making such changes will be charged to the client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-2-website-hosting:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;4.2 - Website Hosting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactically Creative provide a hosting service for all our clients, past and present. This hosting service is usually part of an ongoing maintenance agreement, however it is also offered in isolation as a stand-alone service. This hosting shall be on Tactically Creative’s own VPS, supplied by Digital Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hosting is supplied by Tactically Creative to the client as a stand-alone service, it should not be confused with a maintenance agreement. The client remains solely responsible for the management of the site. Tactically Creative shall only be responsible for the maintenance of our server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-3-a-b-testing:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;4.3 - A/B Testing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All arrangements for the provision of A/B testing supplied by Tactically Creative to the client shall be specified in an individual contract. The arrangement is subject to all the T&amp;amp;Cs in this document, and the same payment and period of cancellation as our other services, such as ‘Website Maintenance’ and ‘Website Hosting’ listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-payment:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;5 - Payment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Payment terms are strictly 30 days unless otherwise agreed in writing beforehand. Whilst any payment due under the agreement remains outstanding, Tactically Creative shall be entitled at our sole and absolute discretion to withdraw provision of any goods or services we would otherwise be obliged to provide under the agreement. Tactically Creative expects payment by electronic bank transfer or online payment within 30 days from the date of invoice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Payments may be made in Euros or US Dollars, provided this has been agreed in advance, and a sum sufficient to cover exchange commission, charges and any other additional expenses incurred has been added to the amount due.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with the Late Payment of Commercial Debts Act 1998, interest will be charged on all payments received outside of payment terms at the rate of eight per cent above the Bank of England Base Rate as applicable on the previous 31 December or 30 June whichever is the most recent. In case collection proves necessary, the client agrees to pay all fees (including all legal fees and court costs) incurred by that process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If for any reason whatsoever we are unable to provide an agreed upon product or service in accordance with these terms and conditions, our liability shall be limited in its entirety to a proportional refund of any fees paid by you for the service or product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;6-unforeseen-additional-costs-or-expenses:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;6 - Unforeseen &amp;amp; Additional Costs or Expenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transfer of domain names to another server can sometimes become a complex and time consuming matter. All administrative fees to third parties and the time taken to organise the transfer will be charged to the client irrespective of any quoted amount set out in the quotation with its specifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional costs incurred in the provision of: stock photography; electronic commerce software; online transaction processing solutions; domain name registration; web space; Internet connection provided by third parties are non refundable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;7-copyright:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;7 - Copyright&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the client guarantees that all elements of text, images or other artwork they provide are either owned by themselves, or that they’ve permission to use them from the rightful owner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the client’s final payment has cleared, copyright will be automatically assigned as follows:
-The client will own the visual elements that Tactically Creative creates for this project. TC will give the client finished files and the client should keep them somewhere safe as Tactically Creative is not required to keep a copy.
-The client will own all elements of text, images and data they provided, unless a third-party owns them.
-Tactically Creative will own the unique combination of these elements that constitutes a complete design and will license that to the client, exclusively and in perpetuity for this project only, unless agreed otherwise. It should be noted that Tactically Creative reserve the right to use any code written throughout any of our projects, elsewhere on the understanding that the result is visually distinct from the original.
-Tactically Creative loves to show off our work and share what we’ve learned with other people, so we reserve the right, with the client’s permission, to display and link to the client’s project as part of our portfolio and to write about it on websites, in magazine articles and in books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;8-domain-name-research-registration:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;8 - Domain Name Research &amp;amp; Registration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the responsibility of the client to provide the domain name for their website at a registrar of their own choosing. Tactically Creative can advise on this matter. Tactically Creative shall be granted access to the client’s domain name registrar for the purposes of assigning the DNS to the appropriate servers. This will result in any previously setup email addresses on that domain not working. If this is the case, Tactically Creative can, although shall not be obliged to; assist with setting up new email accounts for the domain as per below (Section 9).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;9-email:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;9 - Email&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst Tactically Creative may be responsible for the hosting and maintenance of the site, TC are not responsible for any email accounts associated to the client’s domain name. The setup, management and ongoing maintenance of any emails are the client’s sole responsibility. Tactically Creative can advise the client on how best to setup email services, and can assist with this process if Tactically Creative are responsible for the domain’s DNS as per above (Section 8)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;10-sub-contracting:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;10 - Sub-Contracting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If necessary Tactically Creative reserves the right, and the client hereby agrees, to allow the use of sub-contractors or agents to work on any aspect of the design or website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;11-consequential-losses:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;11 - Consequential Losses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If for any reason whatsoever Tactically Creative is unable to provide an agreed product or service in accordance with these terms and conditions, our liability shall be limited in its entirety to a proportional refund of any fees paid by you for the service or product. The entire risk as to the quality and performance of the website or other services is with the client. In no event will Tactically Creative be liable to the client or any third party for any damages, including, but not limited to, service interruptions caused by acts of god, the hosting service or any other circumstances beyond the control of Tactically Creative, any lost profits, lost savings or other incidental, consequential, punitive, or special damages arising out of the operation of or inability to operate the website or other services, failure of any service provider, of any telecommunications carrier, of the Internet backbone, of any Internet servers, your or your site visitors&amp;rsquo; computer or Internet software, even if Tactically Creative has been advised of the possibility of such damages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;12-advice-and-consultancy:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;12 - Advice and Consultancy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any advice given in respect of software, hardware, programming, design, purchasing, hosting, training, upgrading, installing or any other advice, suggestion, recommendation or otherwise of any product or service provided by us or by a third party, whether introduced by us directly or indirectly is accepted by you as an opinion. You further agree to indemnify us of all liability with regard to any decision or action performed by you that may or may not be a direct or indirect result of any contact or dealing with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our consultancy service and general advice is, by its nature, subjective. It is up to you whether you decide to follow our ideas and suggestions. It is not possible and we do not guarantee that any of those ideas and suggestions will increase traffic to your site, improve your ratings with search engines or boost sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;13-training:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;13 - Training&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactically Creative endeavour to provide appropriate training where appropriate. The outcomes of training personnel in whatever activities agreed, are not readily quantifiable and as such we cannot accept liability for any training we provide not meeting the client’s or the trainee’s expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;14-right-to-assign:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;14 - Right to Assign&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Agreement is personal to the client and they may not assign it without our prior express written consent. Should the client transfer ownership of the website as part of a transfer of ownership of a business then the new owners will need to come to a new agreement with Tactically Creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;## 15 - Communication&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactically Creative’s preferred method of communication is by email. Invoices and quotes will be sent by email and shall form a legal document just as if sent by traditional post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design process will be undertaken in person if possible or by Skype conferencing, sample Internet design publication on Tactically Creative’s website, or any other method as appropriate to the client’s particular circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;16-cancellation-and-termination:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;16 - Cancellation and Termination&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactically Creative may, by written notice, terminate the Agreement between us &amp;amp; the client immediately upon the happening of any of the following events. * The client fails to pay any invoice which has become due. * The client commits a material breach of any of the terms of the Agreement between us &amp;amp; them. * The client enters into or proposes a voluntary arrangement or composition with their creditors or reconstruction of their debts or their directors make a declaration of solvency for the purpose of a members&amp;rsquo; voluntary winding up, or if notice is given of a creditors&amp;rsquo; meeting in connection with a creditors&amp;rsquo; winding up, or if a special resolution is passed that they be wound up by the court, or if an administrative or other receiver is appointed, or if the court makes and administration order or order that they be wound up by the court, or if they cease to carry on business or are unable to pay their debts within the meaning of the Insolvency Act 1986 Section 123.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should Tactically Creative decide to terminate the Agreement between us &amp;amp; the client immediately upon the occurrence of one of the above circumstances, we reserve the right to exercise any other rights which we may have against the client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reserve the right to remove from the Internet any website or other service which we display on the client’s behalf upon the occurrence of one of the above circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we terminate the Agreement upon the occurrence of one of the above circumstances, we will not refund any monies paid by the client to us. If at any point during a Project the client wishes to cancel, they may do so but will be invoiced up to the full amount quoted based on the degree to which the work has been completed and on the extent to which time has been allocated to the project that cannot be effectively used to generate revenue that would be otherwise lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the event that Tactically Creative terminates a service contract for any other reason, a refund equivalent to the unused portion of the current payment period will be the maximum liability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;17-waiver-and-interpretation:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;17 - Waiver and Interpretation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should Tactically Creative waive any of these terms on an individual basis, this shall not affect the validity of remaining clauses or commit Tactically Creative to waive the same clause on any other occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These terms and conditions shall prevail over all terms and conditions of the client’s customary practice or any previous course of dealing between us and the client. Any variation to these terms and conditions shall be inapplicable unless agreed between us &amp;amp; the client before we commence any work on their behalf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work, services or products are only supplied in strict accordance with these terms and conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The provision of work, services or products by us is only undertaken on the understanding that the client has read and accepted these terms and conditions in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By agreeing to these terms and conditions the clients statutory rights are not affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This contract shall be subject to English Law. In the event that Tactically Creative is not entitled to rely on a term or terms in this contract, then Tactically Creative may also be allowed to cancel all rights and obligations under this contract, or to hold all other clauses as valid entirely at their sole discretion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No terms or conditions endorsed upon, delivered with or contained in the client’s purchase order, confirmation of order, specification or other document will form part of the contract simply as a result of such document being referred to in the contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The client must ensure that the terms of its order and any applicable specification are complete and accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;18-confidentiality:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;18 - Confidentiality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In connection with our contract, each party may receive or have access to commercially or personally valuable technical and non-technical confidential or proprietary information (“Confidential Information”) of the other party. Confidential Information includes all information, whether oral or written, relating to the business of a party that is not generally known or available to others, including, without limitation, source code and documentation for software, trade secrets, customer lists, pricing strategies, marketing and business plans, information concerning a party’s vendors, and a party’s contemplated plans, strategies and prospects. Each party acknowledges and agrees that any Confidential Information received or obtained from the other party will be the sole and exclusive property of the other party and may not be used, disseminated or disclosed except as may be necessary to perform the obligations required under this Agreement or as may be required by law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;19-relationship-of-the-parties:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;19 - Relationship of the Parties&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship of the parties in connection with this agreement and the contract is that of an independent contractor relationship, and no partnership, joint venture or employee/employer relationship is intended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;20-ethical-policy:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;20 - Ethical Policy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reserve the right to refuse to provide services for any company and it’s associated services which does not accord with our ethical policy, or we judge to be unfit due to content or intended purpose. This includes, but is not limited to, companies or sites containing or promoting adult oriented material such as pornography, companies or sites which promote hatred towards persons belonging to any ethnic group, religion or sexual orientation and companies or sites which infringe copyright or are contrary to UK or other relevant national or local laws or regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;21-force-majeure:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;21 - Force Majeure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither party shall be deemed in default of this agreement or the contract to the extent that performance of its obligations or attempts to cure any breach are delayed or prevented by reason of any act of God, fire, natural disaster, accident, riots, acts of government, or any other cause beyond the reasonable control of such party; provided, that the party whose performance is affected by any such event gives the other party written notice thereof within ten (10) business days of such event or occurrence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;22-notice:9b10c1f64082d3869fd4cb1f85809430&#34;&gt;22 - Notice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any notice, approval, request, authorisation, direction or other communication in connection with this agreement and the client (‘Notice’) must be made to Tactically Creative, by email to jamiedumont@icloud.com. All communication and Notice to the client by Tactically Creative, shall be considered delivered and therefore, given for all purposes; if sent to the email address provided by client.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>