<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Tactically Creative</title>
    <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Tactically Creative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 08:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>London Fizzle Meetup - June 2015</title>
      <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/post/fizzle-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/post/fizzle-talk/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-brilliant-evening:c9033999b9835a7dfef93e5745ed10aa&#34;&gt;A Brilliant Evening!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I&amp;rsquo;d like to send a big &lt;strong&gt;&amp;lsquo;Thank You!&amp;rsquo;&lt;/strong&gt; to Chris, Rob &amp;amp; Heena who did a wonderful job organising a brilliant event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The online &lt;a href=&#34;http://fizzle.co/?aid=8451&#34;&gt;Fizzle&lt;/a&gt; community is a wonderful resource, full of amazing people doing amazing things; but it really comes to life when you meet these people in person. It was a great honour to be asked to speak in front of them, and share my knowledge of building websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a website is the cornerstone for any online entrepreneur, and it&amp;rsquo;s relevance is becoming greater as time passes. However, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of information out there, which can make the process utterly confusing to the uninitiated. The problem isn&amp;rsquo;t the volume of information though, it&amp;rsquo;s the &amp;lsquo;noise&amp;rsquo; within. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of good advice (signal) and a lot of terrible or irrelevant advice (noise), and separating them can be tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My talk aimed to cut through the noise and deliver a small dose of signal to get everyone started. I decided to write my talk up to serve as a point of reference to everyone there. It has the same content as my talk, plus a bit more. I&amp;rsquo;ve included more advice, along with links to what I feel are the most relevant, and important articles out there for anyone building a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site can be found here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://fizzle-london.netlify.com&#34;&gt;On the Creation of Websites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-line-in-the-sand:c9033999b9835a7dfef93e5745ed10aa&#34;&gt;My line in the sand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may have read in my casestudies, I&amp;rsquo;ve moved away from Content Management Systems like Wordpress for my client work, and have other systems (namely static solutions) that I feel are more suitable. I brought this up during my talk, as &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; talking about technology and platforms was going to tough to avoid. When Wordpress came up, and I spoke about how I don&amp;rsquo;t feel it&amp;rsquo;s the most practical option anymore, I received a healthy dose of skepticism from some of the guys there who use Wordpress themselves. I completely expected that, but the insights that came from the resulting debate were interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually sat down and had this discussion with &lt;em&gt;other developers&lt;/em&gt; before, so it was nice to get into a bit of a debate about the pro&amp;rsquo;s and con&amp;rsquo;s of each option. We know how fervently a developer can defend their platform/language/text editor of choice. We&amp;rsquo;re almost fanatical about our beliefs. Having to justify why I&amp;rsquo;ve abandoned an industry standard like Wordpress and shy away from the heavy-handed contracts that most designers/developers use was a really healthy thing for me to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s clear that I&amp;rsquo;ve drawn my line in the sand, and &lt;strong&gt;I offer what I truly believe to be the best service I can&lt;/strong&gt; for my clients. That&amp;rsquo;s required me to approach problems differently and look beyond the obvious solutions. This goes against the grain, and I&amp;rsquo;m comfortable with that, because I believe in what I&amp;rsquo;m offering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World</title>
      <link>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/post/helloworld/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 11:57:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tactically-creative.co.uk/post/helloworld/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Those two immortal words that any developer will know instantly. They symbolise every coffee-fuelled &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Eureka&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; moment and every knowing &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;A-Ha!&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;. They represent learning, understanding and success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fact-1:b0550240c0a1b7c12779ff8220a94c0f&#34;&gt;Fact #1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;Hello World&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; first came about when Brian Kernighan instructed would-be programmers on how to create a simple program, whose only purpose is to output those two little words. The phrase originates from a passage in his book; &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;A Tutorial to the Language B&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;. That was in 1972, and since then, &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Hello World&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; has come represent many programmers and developers first steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has become the de-facto result that novices create when learning basic computer science principles, or even when experienced professionals are learning a new language. It is the proof of concept, and a gateway to ever-increasing knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember my first &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;HW&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; was written in Visual Basic, which my uncle taught me as a child. Once I had that cracked, it was a short step to building a calculator, mimicking Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s own; and then onto larger, complex database driven systems. That &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Hello World&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; became the starting point for the rest of my professional life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fact-2:b0550240c0a1b7c12779ff8220a94c0f&#34;&gt;Fact #2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;tactically-creative-is-here:b0550240c0a1b7c12779ff8220a94c0f&#34;&gt;Tactically Creative is here!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst Tactically Creative has only officially been around for a few months, this moment has been a long time coming! About two years ago, I set out with a mission of making websites for small businesses easier to use, less of a productivity blackhole and far more cost effective. I wanted people to *gasp* enjoy building their website again, rather than dreading the mine-field of publishing new content and making changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Tactically Creative exists to make building and maintaining your business website a breeze, and also fun again! We focus specifically on developing static sites and web apps that provide huge advantages over the go-to solution of Wordpress or similar CMS. We believe that static sites are increasingly the best solution for many businesses, and whilst that idea swims against the current; we&amp;rsquo;re here to show you that the status-quo isn&amp;rsquo;t all it&amp;rsquo;s cracked up to be!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s to &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Hello World&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>