<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Casestudies on Jamie Dumont</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/casestudy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Casestudies on Jamie Dumont</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 15:07:03 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/casestudy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Jake Morrell</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casestudy/jakemorrell/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 15:07:03 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casestudy/jakemorrell/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A band’s need of a website is not uncommon, but finding the right
website can prove tricky for the uninitiated. A band’s site functions
very much as a small business’ site does, yet without the clear &amp;amp; direct
financial objective; which can make it very difficult to build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site also has to become the band’s online ‘home’ that grows with
them. Needing something so personal makes finding an off-the-shelf
solution tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/qtctc_asset_jakeband.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Jake Morrell&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;country-roots:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Country roots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Jake Morrell approached me, he was a musician who had recently
decided that his band should start taking their music seriously, and
start building up a reputation and solid fanbase. Up until that point,
he had been an enthusiastic and talented musician, but had yet to treat
his music as a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the decision was made to make a go of it, Jake recognised that his
current website was not up to the task. If he wanted the band to grow in
popularity, it was clear that their website needed attention if it was
to capture everything that was brilliant about their music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;templates-without-soul:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Templates without soul&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve already said, finding an off-the-shelf solution for a website
as personal as a band’s can be really tough; even more-so when that
band’s identity &amp;amp; sound is as unique and different as Jake’s. He had
been finding that none of the templates and themes he had found really
felt ‘right’ for his band, and the designer in him kept thinking there
must be a better alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He wanted to avoid becoming ‘just another band’, and blending in with
the herd. Jake’s music instantly stands out the moment you hear it, but how
could he stand out online? After looking through his options, he was
confidant that a theme or template, no matter how well designed and
built could never quite capture the band’s identity and their
aspirations for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jake wanted a site that would act as a hub for all his online
communication with his fanbase. Social media was working well in
generating interest, but without a focal point it struggled to create any real traction.
Consolidating his band’s identity into a central site would allow him to
manage and cultivate the band’s image as it grew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also had a problem with his current site that needed solving; he
couldn’t update it! If the site was to grow and become the band’s focal
point, it would need to be simple to update and keep current. The
existing site also didn’t offer any responsive design elements for
mobile viewers. Jake had no analytics to confirm that many of his views
came from portable devices, but was fairly sure that a significant
percentage would have benefited from it. That instantly told me that I
needed to incorporate responsive design into the build, but also some
analytics tools to provide data for later optimisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-new-perspective:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;A new perspective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with a band was a new experience for me. Whilst I&amp;rsquo;m very
comfortable working with small businesses and their objectives; I was
left scratching my head when it came to the music industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where a strong process and working relationship between clients
and their designers comes into play. I could have gone away and done
mounds of research on the music industry and discovered what makes a
successful website in this industry. That would have given me a very
broad overview of the issues facing Jake, but would have left me
with exactly that: a broad view. I needed specific, actionable insights
into Jake’s industry, and what issues it was that he saw and needed
solving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By working closely with Jake throughout, I was able to use him as the
project’s compass. He would indicate a direction or potential problem;
and I would dig through the available data and come up with a suitable,
relevant solution. I’ll happily hold my hands up and say that I
missed the mark on occasions, which only proves why I advocate a close
and ongoing relationship with clients. Any wrong turns
were quickly identified in our regular meetings and conversations, and
we got back on track with little time or resources lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-personal-touch:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;The personal touch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designing an experience for something as personal as a band’s site was
always going to be a challenge. In business, often data and good
practises based on the financial objectives for the site can inform much
of the design. The design decisions for a band, or any personal site,
can be much more arbitrary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I was concerned whether I was the right choice for Jake,
as there are other design companies who concentrate on this sector
exclusively. However, he already had a very clear vision of what he
wanted from the site. What he needed from me was the knowledge and
experience needed to make the strong visual direction he had decided
upon a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an experienced designer (career pre-music) Jake took on the design
himself. The results had exactly the right tone and atmosphere that
suited the band down to the ground. It needed to be simple, honest and
friendly; all sentiments that were captured perfectly because they came
direct from the original source of the band’s identity: Jake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;over-to-me-act-i:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Over to Me - Act I&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This left me focussing heavily on the technical side of the site. When
Jake initially approached me he was asking for a site based on the
almost ubiquitous platform, Wordpress. As I had extensive experience
creating and managing Wordpress sites, I started without a second thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jake’s two key prerequisites were responsive design, and an easy way of
updating the site regularly. Whilst Wordpress was (and always has) been
geared around ‘Posts’, I knew that ‘Custom Post Types’ and various
other plugins would provide the functionality we required for managing
content such as a listing of Jake’s upcoming gigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsive design was something that I had worked with before, but
never from the ‘ground up’ on a new build. For this reason I used a popular and well
documented framework: Foundation. This gave me a good solid system to
work from, and an array of elements that would cover the initial site
build, and any future feature requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt that using two widely available, well established pillars of the
web development world would give Jake a future proof website that could
be easily worked on by almost any developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-wrong-turn:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;A wrong turn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foundation provided a very strong framework to begin building on, however
it was not without it’s problems. Most popular frameworks such as
Bootstrap and Foundation are quite opinionated as standard, and I found
myself overriding much of Foundation’s default styling. This was, I
felt, was a price worth paying to keep the site’s codebase future proof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, once I had completed portions of the site and began testing them, I became
increasingly upset with what I had built. Whilst Jake was very happy
with the site, I felt that the code supporting it was heavy,
overworked, and thanks to the amount I had altered Foundation; far less
future-proof or standardised than I had hoped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To top it off, I felt that Wordpress, as with Foundation, was too
prescriptive for this project. It forced upon us the notion of ‘Posts’,
when really we wanted nothing of the sort! The editing interface was, as
with all Wordpress sites, very ‘messy’. Wordpress as standard displays
far too many options and menu items for someone who wants to update
their gigs and write the odd blog post. This can of course be hidden
away, but why should we have to force the system to do less like this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew that Jake was self-hosting the site, and I likely wouldn’t have any
input on the site once it was launched. This begged the question of how
to manage the Wordpress updates. Did I really want to burden Jake
with updating the install and it’s associated plugins himself, or having
to get me to do it periodically; just to keep the site secure? All of
this seemed unnecessary for what should be a simple site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back to the drawing board…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-me-act-ii:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Back to Me - Act II&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I wanted to resolve was the restrictions that Wordpress
was imposing on the site. It was bloated, complicated and needlessly
complex for this project; so I set out to find the antithesis of this.
I was sure that the answer would be found in ditching the database,
and relying on ‘static’ web pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, I had been playing around with the static site generator,
Jekyll. For those unfamiliar, Jekyll takes templates written in a language called Liquid,
and combines those with content files written in Markdown, and builds the
site into flat, static HTML documents. This results in an incredibly
fast, stable site that can be hosted almost anywhere. Jekyll was always
considered a blogging tool for ‘hackers’, but it’s press as the basis of
Obama’s online fundraising campaign has caused a resurgence in the
popularity of static sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had enough experience building small, quick sites with it to know
that it would work well in this situation; the only issue was how to add
content in a non technical manner. At that time, there was no easy way
to manage content in non-technical manner, everything was done through
Markdown files. I needed something with a suitable interface for Jake
to easily keep the site current, and manage logic surrounding gig listings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution came in the form of a half-way house between Wordpress and
Jekyll: a flat-file CMS called Statamic. Whilst akin to Wordpress in
functionality, it had a structure far closer to a pre-build Jekyll site;
using templates, YAML config files and Markdown content files to
dynamically render the page. Fortunately, Statamic has brilliant
HTML caching, effectively allowing the site to serve static files to
users, but with a dynamic twist when required. This provided the all
important GUI for Jake to work with, and a lightweight system that could
output static files in most instances, reducing load times and improving
the user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My concern over Foundation caused me to take a deeper look at the way I
build my websites. I no longer considered an all-encompassing
framework to be a universal ally. Foundation, like Bootstrap, works well
for quick prototyping but, as I found; poorly in production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution came from creating a bespoke, SASS-based framework loosely
based Harry Robert’s InuitCSS. I used Object-Orientated-CSS (OOCSS)
methodology to build functionality ‘outwards’ from the core of what the
site needed to do right now; rather than ‘inwards’ from a rather
speculative position of what the site &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; need to do in the future.
The result was a lightweight, fast, highly extensible and future proof
framework that could support the site for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-semi-static-renaissance:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;A Semi-Static Renaissance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results speak for themselves. Not only does Jake prefer the vastly
simplified user-interface of Statamic, but the performance meets my
expectations. We’ve managed to achieve some solid loading times, and
Statamic has proved incredibly stable, with straightforward development.
I hope to spend more time with Statamic in the upcoming months to make
it even faster for my clients and their users, as I feel it has great
promise as my “go to” solution for small websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of a database means that the site is far less vulnerable to
security risks, and whilst theoretically still at risk due to the
dynamic nature of the site; it is far, far less likely to be
compromised. In the event it is, getting the site back online is as
simple as replacing some files in a directory, which is the work of 10
minutes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OOCSS framework has allowed for simple ongoing development of the
site. Adding new features is simple, as they extend
existing ones, or bolt-on with no complications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-learned:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;What I Learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;wordpress-is-not-the-solution:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Wordpress is not the solution&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After exploring various CMS options, I have concluded that Wordpress
should no longer be my standard solution, as in most cases, it’s
probably not the best tool for the job. In fact, the more time I spend
with other systems such as Statamic, and static-site-generators (SSGs);
the more I believe that Wordpress will very rarely be the best tool for
my projects now, if ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;an-intelligent-css-architecture-is-worth-it-s-weight-in-gold:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;An intelligent CSS architecture is worth it’s weight in gold.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s probably not the best way to articulate what I&amp;rsquo;m trying to say,
as such an architecture probably weighs next to nothing! However, it
can’t be denied that a considered approach to writing (S)CSS pays
dividends the longer you expect a website to last. Having a well written
one is not only beneficial for performance and ease of development
initially, but can prove to be cost-saving in the long term, when
compared to refactoring the CSS over the lifetime of a website to
accommodate new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;communication-is-key:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Communication is key&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learnt so much on this project, both generally, but also from Jake.
I learnt how to deal with the objectives of a website when there’s no
direct financial correlation to site performance and it’s traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most important thing I learnt was that my process of
constant communication and involvement with the client directly, can’t
be undervalued. Compared to, perhaps more ‘traditional’, methods of
running a project where the client is kept at arms-length and
periodically presented to; the new approach saved both Jake and I time,
and meant we were both much happier with the final outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-03-march-2015:07494fbbad1e8cf758051057f3ca914f&#34;&gt;Update: 03 March 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I thought I’d attach a quick update to this case study. I’ve
continued work on Jake’s site over the past few months, something
neither of us thought would happen. This ongoing work is partly due to
the affinity that I feel towards the project and the band, but also the
results that I’ve produced.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working further on optimising the site and the server setup for
Statamic, I’ve been able to achieve some incredible page load times
(~200ms from a cold cache!). This sort of speed increase has
dramatically improved the UX of the site, and it’s suitability for use
on mobile devices; even those with slow connections!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My work with Statamic on subsequent projects has also confirmed that
Wordpress is no longer a relevant tool for my work. I’ve completely
fallen for Statamic and other static systems. I’ve since updated all of
my previous client work to be based on Statamic (at zero cost to my clients). Replacing
the legacy Wordpress sites from my portfolio was a large time
investment for me, but completely worth it. All my clients are
reporting that they love the new CMS, and it means that I can manage
fewer systems. Everyone wins!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Calum Mallory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casestudy/calummallory/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 15:06:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casestudy/calummallory/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Calum Mallory is an individual with some extraordinary interests, and
the skills to go with them. He describes himself as a “climber, alpinist
&amp;amp; mountaineer”, and he certainly lives up to all three titles! Since
2013, he has been working towards tackling his biggest challenge: Mount
Everest. I was thrilled when he asked me to help out with this
journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/qtctc_asset_calum.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Calum Mallory - Climber&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-i-met-calum:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;When I met Calum…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t lie, I was a touch disappointed when it turned out he wanted
me to make a website, and not go on the climb with him! C&amp;rsquo;est la vie!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first met Calum when learning how to ice-climb. Calum was my instructor, and over a number of weeks
taught me how to become an ice-climbing instructor myself at Ellis
Brigham’s indoor ice wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Calum mentioned he was planning on climbing Mt. Everest, and needed
some help getting together a website and promotional materials to help
raise funds for the trip, I immediately offered to help. Not only did
I have experience building websites for charity focussed expeditions
with Action Challenge, but couldn’t resist taking on such a different
project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-started:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Getting started…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the site had the clear purpose of promoting Calum as a climber,
and raising funds for his expedition, it was also a very personal site.
Fresh from my recent work with Jake Morrell and his band, personal
sites were definitely at the front of my mind, and I quickly started building a brand for Calum and his exploits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branding is something that I rarely do. By the time most companies
start working with me, their brand is already well established and very
little can change. As with my work with Jake Morrell, I was stepping
out of my comfort zone yet again, and testing my skills in a different
area of design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After conducting some initial research into similar sites and campaigns,
an issue that both Calum and I agreed on, and were concerned
with; was the &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; of the brand. We wanted to avoid getting caught up
with the “extreme sport” angle of what Calum does. Given the nature of
his work, and his age; it would have been all too easy to punch out some
relatively generic brand and site that catered to the extreme sport
market, but did nothing to differentiate Calum from his peers. Being
quite inexperienced with brand design, I was concerned that there was
a danger that we could slide towards comfortable stereotypes, even
whilst conscious of this potential pitfall. Throughout the process, I
pledged to remain vigilant for cliches and stereotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst Calum is young, his personality and his attitude towards climbing
are far more mature. He’s incredibly understated and lets his climbing
do all the talking. The only thing that perforates this calm, considered
personality is his enthusiasm for climbing. It’s clear when you meet him
that climbing &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; his life. I immediately associated him with an era
of climbing when it wasn’t about all the shiny, high-tech kit and the
sponsorship deals; but was much purer, and just about the climbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those familiar with outdoor brands, I felt he was more
&lt;strong&gt;Patagonia&lt;/strong&gt;, than &lt;strong&gt;Arcteryx&lt;/strong&gt;. With that in mind, I began basing his
image around the old ‘Chouinard’ brand that eventually evolved into
Patagonia. I took inspiration from the colours that are now considered
‘vintage’ &amp;amp; ‘retro’, and set out to keep the design restrained &amp;amp;
purposeful, much like the industrial design of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-logo:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;The logo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A logo is a logical place to start when designing a brand, and it’s
always a thought-provoking process. The fundamentals are the same as
copy-writing. You condense everything about the company or person, into
as fewer elements as possible, whilst still communicating as much
as possible. This distillation process results in simplicity, which has
a far greater chance of being understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to engage a passer-by, a logo must not only be aesthetically
simple, but also have hidden or implied meaning and content. This often
presents itself as wit or humour, and rewards the passer-by for their
attention, and prompts them to engage further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst there are similarities between brand and website design, they are
also wildly different! It’s fair to say that logos are not my normal cup of
coffee…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, rather than consult a logo designer, Calum opted for me to have
a crack at it first; as he loved the enthusiasm that I had for the
project. I decided to tackle it exactly as I do with the rest of my
design: slowly and iteratively. Instead of hoping for some divine flash
of inspiration (as any creative will tell you, they are rare and not to
be relied upon) I chose to start with a logo that Calum liked during
our research, and iterate from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed was a series of logos that started out rather ugly but had
a solid idea behind them; and were then slowly refined. We felt our
resulting logo communicated enough about his work, without straying
towards the extreme sports angle we feared might be a result. By
starting with a very simple idea, and slowly (and carefully) refining
it, only adding what was necessary; we ended up with something that we
feel represents Calum personality perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;content:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calum was really enthusiastic about the website once he saw the brand
coming together. He began flooding my inbox with photos we could use and
content that could make up the website. It was a refreshing change, as
often website projects suffer from not enough, or irrelevant content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, content is the hardest part of the site to crack. It’s certainly
the most crucial, and without it; all attempts at design fall a little
flat. With Calum supplying so much raw material to work with, I could
be quite ruthless with the edit. I wanted to concentrate
Calum’s message into as fewer words as possible, but not so few that
the communication was compromised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, Calum found this approach to editing a little
brutal, and felt I was cutting too much. However, as the content
slowly started coalescing into pages &amp;amp; paragraphs, he saw that
concentrating what he was saying into as few words as possible worked.
What was left had impact, and engaged the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the logo development, I had also created a number of other
vectors. We agreed that it would be a shame for these not to make
the cut, so they became part of the page layout. They added visual
elements other than photos, which was a point of difference to Calum’s
competition. Their sites were incredibly image heavy, and felt a little
bogged down by them both technically and editorially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;video:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One element however would come to dwarf the rest of the content. Calum had been
working with his climbing partner, Molly Hughes, and Mark Leary, a video
director; to create a short video to summarise the team, their
personality and the challenge that they faced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear as soon as the video was mentioned that it would play a
large role in a user&amp;rsquo;s experience of the site. I knew that the two would have to
compliment each other and work together. If we ended up with a video
that fought with the website around it, the experience could be
confusing and all the good work we had done with Calum in developing his
brand would be compromised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was decided that we should have a chat with Mark, and find out his
plans for the video, and his thoughts on the brand that we had
developed. Fortunately, we found ourselves on the same page. When Mark
explained his plan for the video, I couldn’t help but nod my head the
entire way through!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bringing-it-together:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Bringing it together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video was finished just before the launch of the site, and I got
my first look at it only a day before the site was due to go live.
After my earlier chat with Mark, I knew there was nothing to worry about,
and that the website and the video would work well together; but I had
no idea just how well the two would gel!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-learned:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;What I learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;have-fun:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Have fun!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project was a chance to have some fun. Calum was incredibly relaxed
about the project, and was enjoying his first taste of building a
website. The hardest part of the process was getting feedback from
Calum, as it was hard to get him to be critical of our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was more apparent was the joy I found in tackling something as
different as a portfolio website for an ice-climbing adventurer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;don-t-let-business-get-in-the-way:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Don’t let business get in the way!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that the site definitely felt more like a personal project than
client work at times. This caused me to stray from the brief on
occasions, and drop many of the fundraising features that were initially
present in the brief. After discussing these omissions with Calum, it
was concluded that we should stick with the site we had built. He liked
that it was his personal space to document his growth as a climber and
the exciting trips he went on; and not a transcription of the various
fundraising pages he was already using. It was different, and by having
that ‘portfolio’ to refer to, it made his fundraising pages stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;let-things-develop-naturally:9f49f445d8a41d1d3051ced2b46d627c&#34;&gt;Let things develop naturally.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throwing myself into brand design was a challenge. It was not
entirely new territory for me, but certainly ground that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t as familiar with. However, by taking the same iterative process
that I use for web development, I think we cracked it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always had an end in mind, but I let the route to that aesthetic
goal develop slowly. This careful approach posed many more questions
than I had anticipated, and brought to light some interesting ideas
that I had not considered previously. Take your time, and the result
will be evidence of that care and attention.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>